<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<component type="desktop-application">
    <id>io.github.garglk.Gargoyle</id>
    <metadata_license>FSFAP</metadata_license>
    <name>Gargoyle</name>
    <summary>An Interactive Fiction Player</summary>
    <description>
        <p>
            Gargoyle is an IF player that supports all the major interactive
            fiction formats.
        </p>
        <p>
            Most interactive fiction is distributed as portable game files.
            These portable game files come in many formats. In the past, you
            used to have to download a separate player (interpreter) for each
            format of IF you wanted to play.
        </p>
        <p>
            Gargoyle includes the AdvSys, Agility, Alan 2 and 3, Bocfel, Git,
            Glulxe, Hugo, JACL, Level 9, Magnetic, Scare, ScottFree, and TADS
            2/3 interpreters.
        </p>
    </description>
    <screenshots>
        <screenshot type="default">
            <image>https://github.com/garglk/assets/raw/screenshots/git.png</image>
            <caption>Photopia running under the Git interpreter</caption>
        </screenshot>
        <screenshot>
            <image>https://github.com/garglk/assets/raw/screenshots/glulx.png</image>
            <caption>City of Secrets running under the Glulxe interpreter</caption>
        </screenshot>
        <screenshot>
            <image>https://github.com/garglk/assets/raw/screenshots/magnetic.png</image>
            <caption>Fish! running under the Magnetic interpreter</caption>
        </screenshot>
        <screenshot>
            <image>https://github.com/garglk/assets/raw/screenshots/tads.png</image>
            <caption>Blighted Isle running under the TADS interpreter</caption>
        </screenshot>
        <screenshot>
            <image>https://github.com/garglk/assets/raw/screenshots/z-machine.png</image>
            <caption>Zork 1 running under the Bocfel interpreter</caption>
        </screenshot>
    </screenshots>
    <categories>
        <category>Game</category>
    </categories>
    <url type="homepage">https://github.com/garglk/garglk</url>
    <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/garglk/garglk/issues</url>
    <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.garglk.Gargoyle.desktop</launchable>
    <releases>
        <release version="2026.1" date="2026-02-07">
            <description>
                <ul>
                    <li>Gargoyle now implements Glk version 0.7.6.</li>
                    <li>Infocom’s graphical games are now playable, with some visual quirks.</li>
                    <li>Support for building with MSVC (thanks to Adrian Welcker).</li>
                    <li>Experimental, disabled-by-default support for Adrift 5 games via the new Frankendrift interpreter (thanks to Adrian Welcker).</li>
                    <li>Support for (and default to) Qt 6 and KDE Frameworks 6.</li>
                    <li>Added graphics scalers hqx and xBRZ.</li>
                    <li>MIDI and graphics support for Adrift games.</li>
                    <li>Image scaling can be specified for Magnetic Scrolls games.</li>
                    <li>Location of game data (save files, transcripts, etc) can be configured.</li>
                    <li>Improved behavior of pasting text with newlines.</li>
                    <li>The scrollback buffer can be saved to a text file (Ctrl-Shift-S / ⌘-Shift-S).</li>
                    <li>Added a toggle for full screen (Alt-Enter / ⌘-Ctrl-F).</li>
                    <li>On Unix, Gargoyle’s XDG data directory name changed from “io.github.garglk/Gargoyle” to just “gargoyle”. The older location is still checked for backward compatibility.</li>
                    <li>Interpreter updates.</li>
                    <li>Various accumulated small fixes and updates.</li>
                </ul>
            </description>
        </release>
        <release version="2023.1" date="2023-02-20">
            <description>
                <ul>
                    <li>$HOME/garglk.ini is loaded on macOS again.</li>
                    <li>Fallback fonts work on macOS again.</li>
                    <li>Better support for non-ASCII filenames on Windows.</li>
                    <li>Transcripts update in real time again.</li>
                    <li>Fixed some cases where Agility save/restore prompts didn’t work on macOS.</li>
                    <li>Fixed media loading in JACL and Hugo.</li>
                    <li>Avoided potential crash with newer versions of SDL2_mixer.</li>
                    <li>Readline-style shortcuts are now available on macOS.</li>
                    <li>Interpreter updates: Agility 1.1.2, Alan3 3.0beta8, Bocfel 2.1.1, Git 1.3.7, Glulxe 0.6.0.</li>
                    <li>New interpreters: Taylormade and Plus, supporting more Scott Adams-style games. ScottFree updated to support graphics. Thanks to Petter Sjölund.</li>
                    <li>Support for glkunix_fileref_get_filename().</li>
                    <li>Color theme support with automatic light/dark following.</li>
                    <li>Optional KDE Frameworks integration to improve text editor behavior.</li>
                    <li>Window size and location can now be saved/restored between sessions.</li>
                    <li>Proper monospace font usage in the Agility interpreter.</li>
                    <li>Z-machine bleeps are now supported.</li>
                    <li>Unifont is used to look up missing glyphs.</li>
                </ul>
            </description>
        </release>
        <release version="2022.1" date="2022-01-30">
            <description>
                <ul>
                    <li>Implements Glk version 0.7.5.</li>
                    <li>Various interpreter updates.</li>
                    <li>Unix and Windows UI now use Qt.</li>
                    <li>New sound backend based on Qt.</li>
                    <li>Experimental Haiku OS support.</li>
                    <li>Migrated from SDL1 to SDL2 (thanks to Manuel Stoeckl).</li>
                    <li>Removed built-in fonts due to licensing issues.</li>
                    <li>Default proportional font is now Charis SIL (“Gargoyle Serif”); default monospace is still Go Mono (“Gargoyle Mono”).</li>
                    <li>Improved font rendering with FreeType tuning (thanks to Tynach).</li>
                    <li>Improved Fontconfig lookup to avoid wrong styles.</li>
                    <li>HiDPI support on macOS.</li>
                </ul>
            </description>
        </release>
        <release version="2019.1.1" date="2019-11-19">
            <description>
                <ul>
                    <li>Fixed font selection on Windows.</li>
                    <li>Fixed interpreter locating on FreeBSD.</li>
                </ul>
            </description>
        </release>
        <release version="2019.1" date="2019-11-03">
            <description>
                <ul>
                    <li>Updated many interpreters.</li>
                    <li>Added text-to-speech support.</li>
                    <li>Built-in fonts support a wider range of Unicode.</li>
                    <li>Full-screen support added.</li>
                    <li>Various accumulated small fixes and updates.</li>
                </ul>
            </description>
        </release>
        <release version="2011.1" date="2011-10-19">
            <description>
                <ul>
                    <li>Native ports are now available for Enlightenment and Open Inkpot.</li>
                    <li>Added Glk 0.7.1 features: line input echo and terminators, window border hint, Unicode decomposition and normalization.</li>
                    <li>Added Glk 0.7.2 features: date and time functions.</li>
                    <li>Added support for Treaty of Babel metadata.</li>
                    <li>Very small text buffers now scroll properly.</li>
                    <li>Hyperlinks are now stored with all 32 bits.</li>
                    <li>The background color in grid windows is now fully applied.</li>
                    <li>Scrollback buffer is truncated on window resize to improve responsiveness.</li>
                    <li>Fixed game launch hangs on OS X 10.7 (Lion).</li>
                    <li>Bundled Liberation Mono fonts were incorrectly marked as proportional; this has been corrected.</li>
                    <li>Added Bocfel 0.6.0 for Z-machine stories; Bocfel is now the default Z-machine interpreter.</li>
                    <li>Glulxe is now the default Glulx interpreter for Superglús story files.</li>
                    <li>Added ScottFree 1.14 for SAGA stories.</li>
                    <li>Interpreter command-line flags are now supported in <code>garglk.ini</code>.</li>
                    <li>Interpreter updates: Alan3 3.0b2, JACL 2.8.5, Glulxe 0.4.7, Git 1.2.9, Level9 5.1.</li>
                    <li>Frotz fixes: correctly handles the fixed-width bit in the header and repositions the cursor after writing to the final grid column.</li>
                    <li>Geas now displays menus correctly.</li>
                    <li>TADS improvements: implements the banner API, supports Unicode, and allows timer events during line and character input.</li>
                </ul>
            </description>
        </release>
    </releases>
    <provides>
        <binary>gargoyle</binary>
    </provides>
    <project_license>Artistic-2.0 AND BSD-2-Clause AND BSD-3-Clause AND GPL-2.0-only AND GPL-3.0-only AND MIT</project_license>
    <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />
    <developer id="io.github.cspiegel">
        <name>Chris Spiegel</name>
    </developer>
</component>
